The sound of a train running alongside a river
The color of sunflowers blooming facing down
The sunset becomes a striped border
Why do I want to cry every time you say "thank you"?
I'm like a child
I thought I'd left all my tears in the fridge
Red rover, red rover, send that girl right over
Goodbye, bystander
We keep walking
Even if at the end of this road isn't Heaven or anything like that
I just want to keep being with you and smiling together
Pride, wishes, and hope
I'll always have them just like you do
When you're scared, so scared, and becoming depressed
I'll protect you, I'll always protect you with everything I have
I promise you to your face
When the Cherry Blossoms Bloom
What beautiful weather.
（川本(かわもと)あかり）いいお天気
Pink cherry blossoms, a blue sky, and white clouds.
桜のピンクと空の青に白い雲
There's nothing like eating rice balls under cherry blossom trees.
桜の下で食べるおにぎりって
また格別ね
Sis, give me one more rice ball!
（川本モモ）お姉ちゃん
おにぎり もう１個ちょーだい
はい はい
Sure. Which kind do you want?
どれがいいかしら
Um, fish flakes, and a chicken nugget too!
（モモ）うんとね…
おかか
あとね から揚げも
The petals have mostly fallen,
（あかり）もうだいぶ
散ってきちゃったけれど…
お姉ちゃん
このくらいの方が好きかな
but I think I like it like this.
It isn't that crowded, so you can view them in peace.
人も少なくなって
ゆっくり見られて
I wonder if Rei has arrived in Yamagata yet.
（川本(かわもと)ひなた）零(れい)ちゃん
そろそろ着いたかな 山形
Maybe.
そうね きっとあっちは
今頃が見頃よ
I bet this is the best time to see them over there too.
Human Shogi is so artistic.
人間将棋なんて風流よね
They wear armor and kimonos and hold it in a big park, right?
（ひなた）広い公園で—
みんなで 甲冑(かっちゅう)や着物を着て
するんでしょ
I bet it looks beautiful under cherry blossom trees.
桜の下で きっときれいよ
Cherry blossoms in full bloom,
the beautiful blue sky, green mountains...
満開の桜ときれいな青空
緑の山々
Wonderful.
すてきね
Lucky him.
（ひなた）いいなぁ
ロマンチックだよね
It sounds so romantic.
It's just like I said.
（島田(しまだ) 開(かい)）だから言ったのに…
I'm a rain-bringer.
俺は雨男だって…
I'm not cut out for outdoor festivals.
野外の祭りには不向きだって
ただでさえ 獅子王(ししおう)戦
ストレート負けで—
On top of that, I'm already feeling shameful because I lost in straight sets at the Lion King Tournament
ここにまで対局を
持ってこられなくて—
and couldn't bring the match here.
みんなに会わす顔がないってのに
Damn that Chairman...
会長のやつ…
It'll be fine! Fine!
（神宮寺(じんぐうじ)崇徳(たかのり)）
いいじゃん いいじゃん
Just go and let everyone cheer you up!
こう どーんと みんなに
励ましてもらってこいよ
Whoops!
おっと
I didn't mean that kind of cheering up, okay?
はげましてって
そういう意味じゃないんだぜ
This is the worst.
最悪…
（桐山(きりやま) 零(れい)）荷物 持ちますよ
I'll carry your bag.
Let's get going.
さあ 行きましょう
（零）…って 何なんすか
What is this?!
What's with this lonely melody echoing throughout an empty train station?!
誰もいない駅構内に響き渡る—
このさみしげなメロディーは！
Why this tune?!
なんでこの曲？
It's a bad omen!
不吉すぎるんですけど
From the City of Shogi, Tendou, Let's Get a Master!
What could I say to apologize?
（島田）何て言って
わびたらいいんだろう…
They're all so kind that I know they would never blame me.
みんな優しいから…
きっと 俺を責めたりしないって
分かってる…
But that just makes it more painful.
だから余計つらい…
I would rather...
いっそ…
I would rather have them berate me.
いっそ思い切り責めてくれた方が…
（おじいさん１）こらっ 開！
Hey! Kai!
You rain-bringer!
この雨男！
What are you gonna do about this rain?
（おじいさん２）
どーしてくれんなよ この雨
This weather is your fault!
（おじいさん１）おめえのせいだべ
You rain-bringer!
（島田の祖父）こんの雨男が
（島田）ふっ …とか言ってたら—
That being said, I'm being berated five seconds after getting here!
到着５秒で責められたよ
Here, hand out towels to the pawns.
ほらっ 駒様たちに
タオルを渡すっぺ
Please, have a towel.
はい タオルどうぞ
It's Shimada, 8-dan!
（駒様１）あ！ 島田八段だ
Thank you.
（駒様２）ありがとうございます
Here! Eat.
（おばあちゃん）はい 食え
It's a new recipe from the Shiono Club.
これが塩野(しおの)クラブの新作
French whale rice cake.
「ラフランス くじら餅」だべ
Delicious. This is great.
うまっ これ うまい！
Ma'am, this is wonderful!
（島田）うまいよ おばちゃん
（おばあちゃん）うん うん
And I was gonna make a bundle selling the new product.
新作の物販で ひともうけしようと
思ってたのに…
Grumble
Stab
But with this rain, it's a wash-out!
こんげえな雨で大打撃だわ
I'm really sorry.
すみません
Big Brother! Kiriyama!
（二海堂(にかいどう)晴信(はるのぶ)）兄者(あにじゃ)！ 桐山！
Wow, kiddo!
（島田）おおっ 坊！
That suits you. It looks good on you.
似合う 似合うぞ！
You were born to wear that, kiddo!
ほんとに すっげー似合うな 坊
It suits him so well.
（花岡(はなおか)）もっ
ほんと よくお似合いで
信玄公(しんげんこう)もかくやと
He's like the feudal lord Shingen himself!
Like a full-sized Boys' Festival doll!
まるで五月人形のようなりりしさ
You've touched this old man's heart!
花岡 感激でございます
うっ うっ…
さて 対戦相手の横溝(よこみぞ)君は？
So where's your opponent, Yokomizo?
（横溝(よこみぞ)億泰(おくやす)）はい？
Me?
Hmm. Yes, yes.
（島田）あー はい はい
これは これは えーと 小早川(こばやかわ)…
And he's like, um... Kobayakawa...
Takakage?
秀秋(ひであき)？
Hideaki?
Hey, what's with that obscure lineup?
（横溝）ねえ 何？
その微妙なラインナップ
42nd Tendou Cherry Blossom Festival Human Shogi
（司会）それでは先手 横溝七段
And now, Yokomizo, 7-dan, has the first move.
P-7f.
７六歩(ふ)
White
Nikaidou
Harunobu
5-dan
White
Nikaidou
Harunobu
5-dan
Black
Yokomizo
Okuyasu
7-dan
Black
Yokomizo
Okuyasu
7-dan
Next, Nikaidou, 5-dan.
（司会）後手 二海堂五段
P-3d.
３四歩
White
Nikaidou
Harunobu
5-dan
White
Nikaidou
Harunobu
5-dan
Black
Yokomizo
Okuyasu
7-dan
Black
Yokomizo
Okuyasu
7-dan
White
Nikaidou
Harunobu
5-dan
White
Nikaidou
Harunobu
5-dan
Black
Yokomizo
Okuyasu
7-dan
Black
Yokomizo
Okuyasu
7-dan
P-6f.
（横溝）６六歩
White
Nikaidou
Harunobu
5-dan
White
Nikaidou
Harunobu
5-dan
Black
Yokomizo
Okuyasu
7-dan
Black
Yokomizo
Okuyasu
7-dan
P-8d.
（二海堂）８四歩
R-6h.
White
Nikaidou
Harunobu
5-dan
White
Nikaidou
Harunobu
5-dan
Black
Yokomizo
Okuyasu
7-dan
Black
Yokomizo
Okuyasu
7-dan
40 Minutes
Later
All right, next, S-6g...
じゃあ 次は６七銀(ぎん)… って
あれ？ はっ！
Wait, huh?
Oh, shoot.
やばいでござる
香(きょう)がいつの間にか
一つあがってるでござるよ
I forgot that a lance moved up!
White
Nikaidou
Harunobu
5-dan
White
Nikaidou
Harunobu
5-dan
Black
Yokomizo
Okuyasu
7-dan
Black
Yokomizo
Okuyasu
7-dan
しまったでござるよ
Crap!
Then...
じゃあ…
In Human Shogi, there's a rule—or goal, I should say—to move all of the pieces.
人間将棋は全駒を必ず動かすという
目標というか決まりがあります
It's a different type of competition, so it's easy to miss something.
いつもと違う戦い方になるので
つい うっかりしちゃうんですよね
Th-Then Bx5e!
（横溝）じ… じゃあ 同角(かく)
White
Nikaidou
Harunobu
5-dan
White
Nikaidou
Harunobu
5-dan
Black
Yokomizo
Okuyasu
7-dan
Black
Yokomizo
Okuyasu
7-dan
では…
In that case...
P-3e.
３五歩
Slice
Whoa! A move that takes advantage of his opponent's error!
（島田）おおっと…
相手の失敗につけ込む
のびのびとした一手だ
White
Nikaidou
Harunobu
5-dan
White
Nikaidou
Harunobu
5-dan
Black
Yokomizo
Okuyasu
7-dan
Black
Yokomizo
Okuyasu
7-dan
さすが お坊ちゃま
That's my young master!
ま… 負けました
I-I lost.
White
Nikaidou
Harunobu
5-dan
White
Nikaidou
Harunobu
5-dan
Black
Yokomizo
Okuyasu
7-dan
Black
Yokomizo
Okuyasu
7-dan
In the 42nd Annual Human Shogi match,
the winner after 96 moves is Nikaidou, 5-dan!
（司会）第42回人間将棋は
九十六手をもちまして—
二海堂五段 勝利
Thank you very much.
ありがたき幸せ
I'm extremely delighted.
恐悦至極(きょうえつしごく)にございます
Master Harunobu, that was marvelous!
晴信様 お見事でございます
Well played, both of you.
お二人とも お疲れさまでした
Here, take a breather, Kobayakawa...
ささ 一服どうぞ　小早川…
It's Yokomizo!
（横溝）横溝です！
You're saying it on purpose, Hanaoka!
わざとでしょ 花岡さん！
All right.
さてっと…
次はいよいよ百面指しか
Next up is the 100-match simultaneous exhibition event.
Chairman, Nikaidou, Okuyasu, and I are participating.
会長と俺と二海堂と億泰で
（零）あっ
（神宮寺）桐山
Kiriyama!
あとはよろしくな
I'm counting on you.
What?!
会長 御指名なんだから
逃げられませんよ
Chairman, you're in the program, so you can't run away!
What?
でも俺…
何か おなかの調子が悪くって…
But my stomach is kind of hurting.
Don't lie.
（島田）うそおっしゃい
I heard you from the hallway excitedly talking about having Yonezawa beef tonight!
今夜は米沢(よねざわ)牛だって
はしゃいでる声が—
聞こえて来ましたよ 廊下から
All of the participants are looking
forward to beating you, Chairman!
参加者みんな
楽しみにしてるんですからね
会長をやっつけるのを
Sheesh.
もう
But I learned my lesson last year.
（神宮寺）去年で懲りたよ
だって ここの人
何か妙に強いんだもん
These people are unusually good players.
Especially the old folks who are
in the club you formed, Shimada.
特に島田の作ったクラブの
じいさん ばあさん
あんな ばあさんが普通に
矢倉(やぐら)とか組んでくるんだぜ
Even the old lady over there would break
through a Fortress defense like it's nothing!
That just isn't normal!
ありえないでしょう 普通
I can't finish the game in two hours!
２時間でなんて終わらないよ
My Yonezawa beef will get cold.
米沢牛が冷めちゃう…
I heard about it too.
（横溝）ああ 僕も聞きました
Tsujii was complaining about doing it last year.
辻井(つじい)さん 去年すごく
ぼやいてましたもん
He said he got whipped.
ギッタギッタにされたって
Tsujii, huh?
おお 辻井か
開会式 あいつ
挨拶でかましちゃってさ
In his greeting at the opening ceremony, he pulled a fast one.
Nice to meet you, people of Yamagata.
（辻井(つじい)武史(たけし)）
山形の皆さん はーじめまして
Love me Tendour...
ラブミー テンドゥ〜
I am Tsujii Takeshi.
辻井武史です
ムッフ フフフ…
I didn't think the locals would be that put off by him.
（神宮寺）いやあ
まさか市民の皆さんが—
あんなにもドン引くなんてな
Of course he said that.
そりゃあ 言うでしょう
言うに決まってるでしょう
There was never any question.
If Tsujii is on stage, he's going to say a pun.
辻井さんが そんな大舞台で
かまさないわけないでしょう
42nd Annual 100-Match
Simultaneous Exhibition
It's time to begin.
（司会）さて お時間です
棋士の皆さん
よろしくお願いします
Players, thank you for your cooperation.
それでは お待たせいたしました
Everyone, thank you for your patience.
好評企画 百面指し
It's the ever-popular 100-match simultaneous exhibition event.
And here are our professional shogi players.
棋士の皆さまの入場です
Hi, everybody! Hello!
（会長）やあ
どうも どうも どうも　ハッハッハ
Master Harunobu!
（花岡）晴信様！
Okuyasu, get in front of the Shiono Club.
（神宮寺）億泰 お前 行けよ
塩野クラブの前
嫌ですよ
Forget it. These people have come to beat you, Chairman.
会長倒しに来てるんですよ
あの人たちは
Oh boy.
（島田）あ〜 もうっ
Guess I don't have much choice.
しかたないな
Okay, how about if I go?
じゃ 俺が行きますか
（島田の祖父）おおっ！ 開
Kai!
All right, grandmas and grandpas. I'm not going to hold back.
（島田）さあ
じいちゃん ばあちゃん
手加減しねーぞ
I wouldn't have it any other way!
望むところだ
You're gonna miss dinner tonight!
絶対 晩飯 食わせねえぞ
I'd like to eat dinner, though.
えー 食べようよ
I came all the way back home, so let's all eat together.
せっかく帰って来たんだから
一緒に
Oh, I see. That makes sense!
おーっと そうか なるほどな
フッハハハッ ハハッ…
（泉田(いずみだ)）いかがですか
島田八段の故郷は？
What do you think of Shimada, 8-dan's, hometown, Kiriyama, 5-dan?
桐山五段
えっと… この人どこかで…
Have I met him somewhere before?
そうだ
That's right.
I'm Izumida with the Yamagata Journal.
「山形ジャーナル」の泉田です
島田さんを取材してた人だ
He did an article on Shimada.
Right. Um, I really get the feeling that everyone here is a strong supporter of Shimada.
あ はい あの…
島田さん すごく地元の人に
応援されてるんだなって…
島田八段の出身は—
His real hometown is more in the back regions of Yamagata.
ここより もっと山形の奥地でね
As the population declines, seniors living by themselves get isolated in their homes in the winter because of the snow.
過疎化が進んで—
冬は雪の中で１人暮らしの老人が
孤立してしまう—
冬の厳しい所です
それに心を痛めて
彼が作ったのが—
He was troubled by that,
so he created the Shiono Shogi Club.
塩野将棋クラブです
Twice a week, a bus goes around to all the seniors' houses to pick them up,
週に２回 巡回バスを出して—
お年寄りの家を回り—
公民館のこたつで将棋盤を囲む
and they play shogi on heated tables at the community center.
将棋を指す人もいれば—
While some play shogi,
others cook non-perishable food for the group in large pots.
大鍋で一緒に
保存食を作ったりもする
And when it's time to go home,
そして帰りには—
they take the daily necessities or ingredients they'd asked for as a group, as he arranged to buy it for them.
まとめて注文を取って
買い出しておいた—
日用品や食材と一緒に家まで送る
島田八段は自分の村から—
Shimada, 8-dan, is trying to arrange for the elderly people to not feel isolated anymore.
孤立する老人をなくす仕組みを—
作ろうとしているんです
He also made the arrangements to sell the non-perishable food and sweets the club makes to the train stations.
塩野クラブで作った
保存食やお菓子を—
道の駅なんかに卸す段取りを
つけたのも 島田八段です
何より それで お年寄りに
元気が生まれたのがすばらしい
Most wonderful of all is how these activities have made the old folks so spry.
Oops, sorry. I didn't mean to bend your ear.
おっと あぁ すみません
ついつい長々と語ってしまって
ああ いえ いいんです
No, not at all!
I'm glad you told me.
聞けてよかった
島田さん 本当は
ずっと獅子王戦のこと—
Shimada has been depressed lately. He wonders how he can apologize to everyone regarding the Lion King Tournament.
みんなに 何て言って謝ろうって
沈んでました
But right now, seeing him smile like that,
でも 今 ああして笑っていて…
it makes me really happy.
僕はなんだか
とてもうれしい… っていうか
I mean...
Really?
そうですか！ あぁ よかった…
I'm glad.
I've been covering him all this time for the newspaper, so I've become totally enamored.
私は ずっと彼を
取材してきたんですが—
いやはや すっかり
ほれ込んでしまいまして
I understand.
（零）分かる！
I totally understand!
分かります！
I see.
（泉田）そうか…
そうですか ハハハッ
Is that so?
When Izumida said that and smiled, he seemed delighted.
（零）そう言って笑う泉田さんは
すごくうれしそうで…
That kind of made me happy in return.
僕までなんだか うれしくなった
まるで自分のことみたいに
I felt connected to it.
And that feeling somehow filled me with joy.
そして それはなんだか
とても幸せな気分だった
Here's butterbur miso, rice balls,
snow greens pickled in salt, and whale rice cakes.
ほいでこれが ばっけみそに—
おにぎりに雪菜漬けに くじら餅
これは冷凍しといた干し柿
And here are some frozen dried persimmons.
You guys are giving me so much again.
ああ またまた おんちゃんたち
こんなにたくさん
Honestly, you never change.
もうっ 変わんないな
We're never gonna change.
変わんねえさ
変わんねえ
Never ever.
So it's okay.
大丈夫だから
No need to rush, Kai.
焦るな 開…
I've been rushing so much that I lost my head.
（島田）焦る気持ちに溺れていた
How many times do I go back to where I started?
何度振り出しに戻ればいいのかと…
I was so lost.
途方に暮れていた
その気持ちはこれからも…
Even from here on out,
消えるわけではないけれど…
that feeling won't go away, but...
Shimada! The train's coming!
島田さん 電車来ますよ
Big Brother! Hurry up, hurry up!
兄者 早く 早く
From the City of Shogi, Tendou, Let's Get a Master!
Right.
さてっと
Now then.
Guess I'll start over again this year and work hard.
また今年も…
一から頑張りますか
（島田）
♪ こわいながらも 通りゃんせ
It's gonna be scary, but you may pass through.
You may pass through.
When the Cherry Blossoms Bloom
A Small Murmur
（川本(かわもと)相米二(そめじ)）
う〜ん どうしたもんかな
I'm not sure what to do.
おじいちゃん 悩んでるわね
You seem troubled, Grandpa.
（ひなた）
次の新作？ おじいちゃん
Is it about your next new creation, Grandpa?
Yeah.
夏に向けて
新商品を編み出したいんだが—
I'm trying to think of something that'd be good for the summer,
何かこうひとつ
ぱーっとしねえんだよな
but I'm not getting any inspiration.
Egg
Chunky
The Baked Crescents are great and have become the shop's signature sweet,
三日月(みかづき)焼きは見事 我が三月町(さんがつちょう)の
名物として定着したが—
but if possible, I'd like one more new showpiece.
できれば もう一つ
新しい目玉が欲しいんだよな
う〜ん …とすると—
Then the name and form should be easy for people to remember and not get tired of,
覚えてもらいやすくて
飽きのこない名前と形
でもって 手土産にもいいように
日持ちのする…
but it also needs to keep for a few days so that it'd be good as a present.
…となると焼き菓子？
So something baked?
（ひなた）えー 待って 待って
Wait, wait!
Long-lasting is important too, but if it's baked, it'll overlap with the Baked Crescents.
日持ちはとっても大切だけど—
焼き菓子だと
三日月焼きとかぶっちゃう
生っぽいのでも
いいんじゃないのかな
Maybe we can go with something that's fresh.
Like strawberry rice cakes,
which don't have a long shelf life but are popular.
ほら いちご大福とか
日持ちしないけど有名だよね
Strawberry rice cakes...
いちご大福か…
I was surprised the first time,
but it turned out well and caught on here.
ありゃあ 最初びっくりしたが
確かにうまかったし定着したな
I see.
なるほど…
いちご大福みたいに 何かこう
思いがけない物が入って—
So something like strawberry rice cakes with a surprising filling, and if we can get a new flavor, that'd be great.
新しい味が生まれるのもいいな
Okay, Hina, for example,
what filling would make you happy?
じゃあ ヒナ 例えばお前だったら
何が入ってるとうれしい？
何が好きだ？
What do you like?
Um, let's see...
えっとね
Maybe apples!
りんごとか
And whipped cream!
あと 生クリーム！
Whipped cream.
（相米二）生クリーム？
Whipped cream?
生クリームか
和菓子に生クリームじゃ
I think putting whipped cream in Japanese-style sweets would kill the merit of them.
Hmmm...
やっぱ和菓子の良さが—
死んじまう気がするっつうか
Hmmm...
I just think that could be heresy.
やっぱ じーちゃんには
邪道に思えるんだよな
But sweet bean paste and whipped cream are delicious together!
え だって だって
あんこと生クリーム
一緒に食べるとおいしいよ
You know, like fruit salad topped with cream or cream on red bean soup!
ほら クリームみつ豆とか
クリームぜんざいとか…
True, fruit salad with whipped cream on top is good.
まあ確かにクリームみつ豆は
クリームがのってて うまいな
Fruit salad with whipped cream on top, huh? It really is tasty.
（あかり）クリームみつ豆か…
（ひなた）うん
（あかり）おいしいわよね
You can't help dropping in at Flower Garden or Mitsuhashi.
（あかり）花(はな)の苑(えん)さんとか
（ひなた）うん
（あかり）みつはしさんとか
つい入っちゃうわよね
But sweets shops are traps, aren't they?
でも… 甘味屋さんって
トラップなのよね
I'm tired.
（あかり）ああ 疲れた
Mitsuhashi         Sweets
何か甘い物 食べて帰ろっか
Should we get a sweet treat before going home?
やった！ 賛成
Yay! Definitely!
It's okay to splurge once in a while, right?
（あかり）いいわよね
たまにはぜいたくしても
Look, the fruit salad is only 350 yen.
ほら みつ豆なんて350円だし
Dazzle
うーん でも あんこはやっぱり
のせたいよね
Dazzle
But I'd want to put sweet beans on top too.
Huff
Me too.
のせたいわよね
Huff
…とすると
あんみつになって430円
Huff
So that would be fruit salad topped with sweet beans for 430 yen.
I guess that's okay. For the two of us, it'd be 860 yen.
Huff
まぁいいか 二人で860円
あっ でも待って 待って
Dazzle
But wait! In that case, for another 100 yen,
we can have it with cream!
Dazzle
それなら いっそ100円足して
クリームあんみつ
Dazzle
Huff
Nice! Cream would be nice!
あ すてき　クリームすてき
Huff
でも そこまでするなら
プラス50円で—
Huff
But if we're going that far,
another 50 yen would get us whipped cream!
Huff
生クリームも絞ってもらえるよ
ちょ ちょっと待って
Huff
Dazzle
Wait! If we're putting whipped cream on top, I'd want apricots too!
生クリームのせるなら
あんずだって のせたいじゃない？
Dazzle
Then I'll have bananas!
（あかり）え？
えー じゃあ私 バナナ
Ta-daaa!
Packed
Final Result
All the toppings
Packed
Total:
1,610 yen
Oh no.
（あかり）しまった…
（ひなた）あああ…
Why does this always happen?
（あかり）なんでいつも
こうなっちゃうんだろう
たかが おやつに1610円も…
We spent 1,610 yen on just a snack!
I'm stuffed. I'm gonna get fat!
おなかいっぱい… 太る…
Even though I'm always stingy to a fault...
いつも これでもかってぐらい
ケチケチ切り詰めているのに
With 1,610 yen, we could've bought 2.3 kg
of chicken at 68 yen per 100 grams.
1610円もあったら
100グラム68円の鶏肉が—
2,3キロも買えたのに
With 2.3 kg, we could've fed the family for five days!
2,3キロあったら
５日は食べられたのに
Sweets shop traps are scary!
（ひなた）
甘味屋トラップって恐ろしい
Your mind goes blank.
頭が こう ぱーってなるし
And you get fat.
あと太る…
This is our punishment for going without Momo.
モモにないしょで行ったから
ばちが当たったんだ
Now we've got to be even more frugal this month.
今月さらに節約しないと…
I regret what we did.
ねえちゃん 反省
What?!
（相米二）
えー おい そこ 沈むなよ
Hey, don't get depressed over there!
…っと最近の話かよ
Was that something recent?
I thought you were going to help me come up with a new idea!
新作のアイデア
出してくれるんじゃねえのかよ
That's right, Momo! How about you, Momo?
そうだ モモ　モモはどうだ？
What filling would you like in a rice cake?
大福とかまんじゅうの中に
何が入ってるとうれしい？
何が好きだ？
What do you like?
Gum?
ガム
What?!
We've got a genius here!
G-Grandpa! Get a grip!
（相米二）天才 来たこれ！
（ひなた）おじいちゃん しっかり
Calm down!
（あかり）落ち着いて
Um... Okay.
（あかり）えっと では
All right, calm down.
じゃあ 落ち着いて
Calm down and we can think it through again.
落ち着いて
もう１回 整理しましょう
Shh, shh, okay, okay.
（あかり）しー しー どう どう
（相米二）お… おお
Y-Yeah.
Okay.
（ひなた）うん
大福に入れたい おいしい物
A tasty filling for a rice cake.
First, red bean paste, of course.
まず あんこでしょ
And sweet green paste.
ずんだ豆でしょ
Walnuts, powdered green tea, apples, strawberries...
あっ くるみ 抹茶 りんご いちご
Chestnuts, sweet potatoes...
（ひなた）くり スイートポテト
（あかり）塩キャラメル
Salted caramel...
あっ あと生クリーム
And whipped cream!
Hey, that again?!
おい またそこかよ
Don't stray too far from Japanese confections!
あんまり和菓子から離れるなよ
If I went along with what you're saying, this would turn into a cake shop!
お前らの言うこと
みんな聞いてたら—
じいちゃん ケーキ屋になっちまう
お前ら ほんとは和菓子 嫌いなの？
Do you kids actually hate Japanese sweets?!
I-I'm sorry! I really like them! I love them!
ご ごめんなさい
好きです　大好きです
It's no good!
ダ〜メ〜
I can't narrow it down! There are too many choices!
絞れない まとまらないよ〜
Sweet green paste, powdered green tea with cream,
strawberry with cream, chestnut...
ずんだに抹茶クリーム
いちごクリーム くり…
Woman want this and that. They're so greedy.
女ってのは あれやこれやと
欲張りだからな
I just can't pick one!
だって 一個になんて
絞れないよ〜
So many different flavors...
いろんな味をいっぺんに…
…って ん？
Huh?
I've got an idea!
ヒナ ひらめいたーっ
（相米二）
どうだい こんな感じか？
Well, like this?
How cute!
ああ かわいい！
だるまさん いた
It looks like a snowman!
へへ… さすが俺
I'm a genius!
（クロちゃん）ニャー
What do you call them?
（あかり）名前は？
March City Puffy-Puffy Snowman!
（ひなた）三月町ふくふくダルマ
The rice cakes are filled with different flavors of bean jam,
and when put together, they look like snowmen.
違う味のあんが入った
大小のお餅を—
２つ雪だるまみたいに
くっつけてるから ふくふくだるま
"Puffy" can also mean "good fortune,"
and I used it twice to double the good luck!
ふくは福とふっくらにかけて—
２回だと福も倍みたいで
縁起よさそうでしょ
Yeah, this is good.
うんうん　確かに こりゃいいな
Two flavors of bean jam in a set, and they're cute too.
２食のあんがセットで味わえて
しかも…
かわいい
Sweet green bean paste and whipped cream, or sweet red bean paste and sweet potato...
ずんだあんと生クリームとか
粒あんとサツマイモとか
中だけ変えれば
バリエーションができるわね
You can make variations by changing just the inside.
It would be nice to change the flavors with the seasons.
季節ごとに変えていってもいいわね
Like limited time flavors...
期間限定とか
秋はくりあん
Chestnut paste in the fall, strawberry cream in the spring...
春はいちごクリームとか
All right!
よしっ
あした ちょっくら
定(さだ)さんたちにも話してみるわ
I'll tell Sada and the others about it tomorrow.
Gotta be positive!
前向きにな
Yay!
やったー
Mom, look.
お母さん 見て見て
I thought up a sweet too.
ヒナもお菓子 考えたんだよ
（モモ）ガブッ
（クロちゃん）吸われる〜
She's eating me!
（ひなた）ねえ おじいちゃん
Hey, Grandpa.
Mom came up with the Baked Crescents, right?
三日月焼きって
お母さんが考えたんでしょ
What did you say?
あ？ なんだと
Dummy!
バカ野郎
I'm the one who worked hard to make the prototype, the mold, and the finishing touches.
苦労して試作して金型も作って
仕上げたのは じいちゃんだ
But the one who thought up the cute shape and name was your mom, Mikako.
だが…
あんなかわいい形と
名前を考えたのは美香子(みかこ)
お母さんだよ
Mikako loved cooking, loved Japanese sweets,
美香子はな
料理が好きで 和菓子が好きで
and would learn by watching others,
then make different "prototype" sweets on her own.
よく勝手に試作品だとか言って—
見よう見まねで いろんな菓子を
こさえてたな
I see.
そっか…
I hope this Puffy-Puffy Snowman makes everyone happy,
just like the Baked Crescents.
この ふくふくだるまも
三日月焼きみたいに—
みんなに喜んでもらえるように
なるといいな
I can't wait for everyone to try it.
早く食べてほしい…
Oh, that's right!
そうだ！
Meowthing
for us yet.
Meowthing for us yet.
Meowthing
for us yet.
Yes, hello?
あっ はい もしもし
Hello?
Rei, good evening!
零ちゃん こんばんは
Huh?
えっ ああ こんばんは
Oh, good evening.
Would you like to come over for dinner tonight?
（ひなた）
今日 晩ごはん食べに来ませんか？
（零）えっと… はい　喜んで
Um...
Yes, I'd love to.
Oh, Rei. Long time no see. How have you been?
あら 零君 久しぶり　元気だった？
（モモ）零ちゃんだ
（あかり）人間将棋 楽しかった？
Rei!
Was the Human Shogi fun?
Yes.
（零）あ はい
雨でしたけど楽しかったです
It was raining, but it was still fun.
Oh, what's all that?
（あかり）まあ なあに？ たくさん
先輩からのおすそ分けです
My mentor shared it with me.
From his hometown in Yamagata.
山形が実家の
He said he couldn't eat all of it, so he offered me some.
食べきれないから
よかったらどうぞって
That's wonderful.
まあ うれしい
Please, come on in!
さあ 上がって 上がって
（ひなた）
その日 桐山君は 山形のお土産を
たくさん持ってきてくれました
That day, Kiriyama brought over all kinds of goodies from Yamagata.
Sis was thrilled the side dishes crossed the bridge and made it over to us.
お姉ちゃんは おかずが橋を渡って
やってきて助かったと喜んで—
We also enjoyed the Puffy-Puffy Snowman I came up with for dessert.
デザートには みんなで—
私の考案した ふくふくだるまを
食べました
And, this is still a secret,
そして これはまだ
ないしょなのですが…
but if I can, I'd like to make Japanese sweets for
a living and someday run the shop with Grandpa.
できれば私は
和菓子を作る人になって—
いつか おじいちゃんと一緒に
お店をやりたいなって思いました
Hinata.
ひなた
A Small Murmur
Your fingers, your chest, your eyes
Are so dazzling there are nights when I get dizzy
They suddenly fall upon me, and it's just so warm
That it feels like I swallowed a seven-colored star
You held me tight, troubling me like a burning spark would
But I was taught to keep walking despite everything
God, please hear me out
For just a little while
Please connect us like that constellation
So that we're never away from each other
So that we're always together
Next Episode Preview
Episode 22
I'm just speaking the truth!
（二海堂）
俺は真実を言ってるだけだ
Don't falter, Kiriyama!
ひるむな 桐山！
What? Is shogi really so minor?
（林田）何？ 将棋って
そんなにマイナーなの？
Give me a break!
（零）おい こら
ざっくり判断にもほどがある
There are limits in
making snap decisions too!
（野口）ハッ ハハハハ
見てのとおり納豆の収穫ですよ
As you can see,
we're harvesting natto.
Hey, can we eat together?
（零）ねえ
一緒に食べてもいいかな？
Illustration: Shimamoto Kazuhiko
Kiriyama,
you bastard...
Hold it
right there!
But I was definitely a guy
who can bring out the sun!
（二海堂）
俺は絶対 晴れ男のはずなのに
来年の人間将棋は快晴で決まりだ
For next year's Human Shogi,
I've decided that it's going to be sunny!
次回も３月のライオンを
お楽しみに
Don't miss the next episode of
"March comes in like a lion"!